Guide to the Industrial Workers of the World Collection,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Industrial Workers of the World Collection,
1916-1922.
Industrial Workers of the World.
0.5 linear ft. (1 box) and 1 (oversize poster).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library Rare Books and Manuscript Library Butler Library, 6th floor 535 West 114th Street New York, NY 10027
MS#1475
7072761
Historical Note
The Industrial Workers of the World (I.W.W.), also known as the "Wobblies", is international union founded in 1905.
The I.W.W. formed in reaction to the AFL's perceived failure to effectively organize the working class in a spirit of revolutionaly solidarity and class-consciousness. Claiming that "an injury to one is an injury to all", the I.W.W. wants to directly confront the ruling-calss. The I.W.W. sees workers as a class ineluctable at odds with the ruling, capitalist class. Through effective organization and strikes the I.W.W. wants to bing about the overthrow of the capitalist ecomonic structure and replce it with a just, cooperative economic and social structure.
As the I.W.W. wab-site states: "Between these two classes a struggle must go on until the workers of the world organize as a class, take possession of the means of production, abolish the wage system, and live in harmony with the Earth."
Scope and Content
A small collection of poems, broadsides, fliers, publications, manuscripts, and letters.
Arrangement
Not organized.
Subjects
Industrial Workers of the World.; Chumley, L. S. (Leland Stanford).; Labor unions--History.; Labor movement--United States--History--20th century.; Socialism--United States--History.; Broadsides; Pahphlets; Poems
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
[source of acquisition] Gift, 11/30/2002 2008-2009-M105.
- Contents List:
  - "International Solidarity" Broadside in Russian and English, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "The Can Opener" Volume 1, No. 3 October 28, 1917. Manuscript in pencil with illustrations 8 pages. Fragile (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photograph of I.W.W. Headquarters "Raided November 15, 1919" (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Co-Operative Corridors Jail Jazzpaper" Volume 1, No. 5 April 13, 1918. Manuscript in pencil with illustrations 16 pages. Fragile (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "The Can Opener" Volume 1, No. 6 November, 1917. Manuscript in pencil with illustrations 10 pages. Fragile (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Industrial Union Manifesto" [recto] and "One Big Union: The Structure of the Industrial System" [verso, circular chart]. William D. Haywood, General Secretary Treasured, 1001 West Madison Street, Chicago, Ill (folded) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Circular letter from the General Defense Committee re. the pamphlet "Shall Freedom Die", undated 1p. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Unionismo Industrial por Vincent St. John Traduccion de A.V.A. Pamphlet, 16 p annotated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Why One Big Union ClubÀ Flyer, October, 1935 Fragile, brittle (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Card "Open the Doors of Freedom" Poem by William Goodhue (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Card: "A Call to Sinn Feiners" Poem by Joe Kennedy (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Industrial Workers of the World Tenth Convention Ball, Chicago November 25, 1916 Advertising pamphlet, 16p. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - The Will of the People Says "Let Them Go Free!" Pamphlet 4p. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - To the Public. And Particularly the Working Man and Women of this Vicinity Flyer, broadside. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "Monster Protest Meeting Against the Hanging of Tom Mooney", March24, 1918. Flyer (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "The Producer’s Age" A Weekly Magazine for Workers, July 20, 1921. Broadside (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - I.W.W.. General Defense Committee. Flyer, signed L.S. Chumley, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Broadside regarding "The Producers", June 5, 1921. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - The Preacher and the Slave and My Wandering Boy. Printed songs (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Fill the Jails Pamphlet by Better America Federation of California, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - The One Big Union. Membership cards (2), signed by Jesse Kennedy (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - I.W.W. logo on card (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - High-Brow Stuff vs. The Dinner Pail. Pamphlet, 8p. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - "The Douglas Co. Jail Jinx" Volume I, No 1. Manuscript (extremely fragile!) (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Cartoon of mail carrier bring large sack of mail to L.C. Chumley. Pencil artwork on envelope (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - "A Detective" by William Haywood. On post-card (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Printing Job Ticket, 10/21/26 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Envelope labeled "Secret Prison Newspaper" (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - "Convention Call for the One Big Union", June 29, 1920. Broadside (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - "Attention Workers!" Broadside The Bank of North Dakota, February1, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - "International Position of the I.W.W." June 1, 1922. Broadside. (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - "Unions Fight for the Right to Strike; "What Do You Think of ThisÀ": "The I.W.W. Trial"; "You and I". Leaflets (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - "To Member of the I.W.W.": Leaflet; "Going to the HarversÀ". Leaflet No 1; "Stop the Split in the I.W.W." Leaflet No 2 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - "To All Marine Transport Workers" Broadside (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - The One Big Union by Forrest Edwards. Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Does the I.W.W. Preach ViolenceÀ Broadside (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Do You Want Mob RuleÀ Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Helen Keller Scores I.W.W. Persecutions. Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - The Unskilled Labor Problem. Broadside (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Smash the I.W.W. Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - The One Big Union of Mine Workers by A.V. Azuara.
  - Oil Field Workers Unite. Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Playing with Dynamite. Editorial November 16, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Metal Workers of America! Unite!. Leaflet (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - I.W.W. General Defense Committee. Broadside, December 31, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Food Those Who Prepare and Serve it. Leaflet (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - L.S. Chumley correspondence, 1918-1919 (21 items) (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - "Workers are You Aware of the Fact that the Manufacturers Association is Scheming to Cut Down Your WagesÀ" Typesd mss (carbon) 4p. (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - "Bulletin" and "Manifesto", undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - "Report on Party Fractions" Manuscript with form (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - "This international strike.. ." Holograph, fragile! (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - "Flare Up Within this Marine Transport Workers IU of the IWW" (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Letters to Joe Fisher, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - "To the American People: Report Upon the Illegal Practices of the United States Department of Justice", November 1920 (pamphlet) (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - "Report to General Executive Board", 1920 (pamphlet) (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - I.W.W. blank stationary (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - "Manifesto of Socialist Industrial Unionism" (broadside) (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - "Publications of the American Russian Institute, Inc." January 15, 1938 (list) (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - "Dialectical Materialism: A Series of Ten Lectures by Charles Chang" Types manuscript. (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - T-bone Slim letter to L.S. Chumley, February13, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - L.S. Chumley. "Statement on trial of 115 members and sympathizers of the I.W.W. in Chicago" (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - "Is It Reason To StrikeÀ" Broadside by General Defense Committee. (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Minutes of N.Y.R.U. meeting of April 29, 1919 signed "Harry". (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Poems:
    - A. Barr poem (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - A.L. T’Rego poem (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Benjamin Richardson poem (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Covington Ami poems (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - D.S. Dietz poem (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Donald M. Crocker poem (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - F.R. Uhde poem (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Gerald Laury poem (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Harold Roland Johnson poem (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Harrison George poem (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - J.H.B. the Rambler (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - J. William Schweitzer poem (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - Lawrence Tully poem (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - Lew Maisel poem (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - Los Angeles Jack poem (Box 1, Folder 65)
    - Mor Goldsmith poem (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - Podmuck Red poem (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - Raymond Corder poem (Box 1, Folder 68)
    - Red Pacific poem (Box 1, Folder 69)
    - Richard Brazier poem (Box 1, Folder 70)
    - Sigismund poems (Box 1, Folder 71)
    - W. Clifford poem (Box 1, Folder 72)
    - Wigand Allen poem (Box 1, Folder 73)
    - Poems by unidentified author (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Miscellaneous envelopes (3) (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Large W.W.I Poster (Mapcase 15-K-6)